<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This DocBook file was created by LyX 2.4.0dev
  See http://www.lyx.org/ for more information -->
<book xml:lang="ru_RU" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.2">
<title>Дополнительные возможности LyX</title>
<chapter>
<title>Введение</title>
<para>Пример:</para>
<para>The Adventure of the Empty Houseby Sir Arthur Conan DoyleIt was in the spring of the year 1894 that all London was interested, and the fashionable world dismayed, by the murder of the Honourable Ronald Adair under most unusual and inexplicable circumstances. The public has already learned those particulars of the crime which came out in the police investigation, but a good deal was suppressed upon that occasion, since the case for the prosecution was so overwhelmingly strong that it was not necessary to bring forward all the facts. Only now, at the end of nearly ten years, am I allowed to supply those missing links which make up the whole of that remarkable chain. The crime was of interest in itself, but that interest was as nothing to me compared to the inconceivable sequel, which afforded me the greatest shock and surprise of any event in my adventurous life. Even now, after this long interval, I find myself thrilling as I think of it, and feeling once more that sudden flood of joy, amazement, and incredulity which utterly submerged my mind. Let me say to that public, which has shown some interest in those glimpses which I have occasionally given them of the thoughts and actions of a very remarkable man, that they are not to blame me if I have not shared my knowledge with them, for I should have considered it my first duty to do so, had I not been barred by a positive prohibition from his own lips, which was only withdrawn upon the third of last month.</para>

<para>Пример с 3&#xA0;колонками:</para>
<para>It can be imagined that my close intimacy with Sherlock Holmes had interested me deeply in crime, and that after his disappearance I never failed to read with care the various problems which came before the public. And I even attempted, more than once, for my own private satisfaction, to employ his methods in their solution, though with indifferent success. There was none, however, which appealed to me like this tragedy of Ronald Adair. As I read the evidence at the inquest, which led up to a verdict of willful murder against some person or persons unknown, I realized more clearly than I had ever done the loss which the community had sustained by the death of Sherlock Holmes. There were points about this strange business which would, I was sure, have specially appealed to him, and the efforts of the police would have been supplemented, or more probably anticipated, by the trained observation and the alert mind of the first criminal agent in Europe. All day, as I drove upon my round, I turned over the case in my mind and found no explanation which appeared to me to be adequate. At the risk of telling a twice-told tale, I will recapitulate the facts as they were known to the public at the conclusion of the inquest.</para>

<para>Можно иметь до 10 колонок, но следует учитывать степень удобства при чтении такого фрагмента документа.</para>
<section>
<title>Колонки внутри колонок</title>
<para>Также можно иметь колонки внутри колонок:</para>
<para>The Honourable Ronald Adair was the second son of the Earl of Maynooth, at that time governor of one of the Australian colonies. Adair's mother had returned from Australia to undergo the operation for cataract, and she, her son Ronald, and her daughter Hilda were living together at 427 Park Lane.<para>The youth moved in the best society&#xA0;– had, so far as was known, no enemies and no particular vices. He had been engaged to Miss Edith Woodley, of Carstairs, but the engagement had been broken off by mutual consent some months before, and there was no sign that it had left any very profound feeling behind it. For the rest {sic} the man's life moved in a narrow and conventional circle, for his habits were quiet and his nature unemotional. Yet it was upon this easy-going young aristocrat that death came, in most strange and unexpected form, between the hours of ten and eleven-twenty on the night of March 30, 1894.</para>
Ronald Adair was fond of cards&#xA0;– playing continually, but never for such stakes as would hurt him. He was a member of the Baldwin, the Cavendish, and the Bagatelle card clubs. It was shown that, after dinner on the day of his death, he had played a rubber of whist at the latter club. He had also played there in the afternoon. The evidence of those who had played with him&#xA0;– Mr. Murray, Sir John Hardy, and Colonel Moran&#xA0;– showed that the game was whist, and that there was a fairly equal fall of the cards. Adair might have lost five pounds, but not more. His fortune was a considerable one, and such a loss could not in any way affect him. He had played nearly every day at one club or other, but he was a cautious player, and usually rose a winner. It came out in evidence that, in partnership with Colonel Moran, he had actually won as much as four hundred and twenty pounds in a sitting, some weeks before, from Godfrey Milner and Lord Balmoral. So much for his recent history as it came out at the inquest.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Дополнительные примеры</title>
<para>Примеры в этом разделе демонстрируют некоторые дополнительные особенности организации мульти-колонок.</para>
<para>Дополнительные возможности использования нескольких колонок см. в <link xlink:href="http://mirror.ctan.org/macros/latex/required/tools/multicol.pdf">документации</link> LaTeX-пакета <emphasis role='bold'>multicol</emphasis>.</para>
<section>
<title>Введение</title>
<para>Чтобы добавить текст введения для нескольких колонок, установите курсор во вставку с многоколоночностью и используйте меню <emphasis role='sans'>Вставка&#x21D2;Введение</emphasis>. Введите текст введения во вставке.</para>
<para>Пример с некоторым текстом введения:</para>
<para role='preface'>And the story continues and continues and continues and continues&#x2026;</para>
<para>On the evening of the crime, he returned from the club exactly at ten. His mother and sister were out spending the evening with a relation. The servant deposed that she heard him enter the front room on the second floor, generally used as his sitting-room. She had lit a fire there, and as it smoked she had opened the window. No sound was heard from the room until eleven-twenty, the hour of the return of Lady Maynooth and her daughter. Desiring to say good-night, she attempted to enter her son's room. The door was locked on the inside, and no answer could be got to their cries and knocking. Help was obtained, and the door forced. The unfortunate young man was found lying near the table. His head had been horribly mutilated by an expanding revolver bullet, but no weapon of any sort was to be found in the room.</para>

<para>Вы также можете использовать заголовок раздела в качестве введения, если используете команду раздела как <emphasis role='sans'>Код TeX</emphasis>. Например, команда</para>
<programlisting language='lyx'>\subsection{Заголовок}</programlisting>
<para>создает подраздел. В этом примере, введение — это заголовок подраздела:</para>
<para role='preface'><!-- \subsubsection{ -->Этот заголовок подраздела — введение<!-- } --></para>
<para>A minute examination of the circumstances served only to make the case more complex. In the first place, no reason could be given why the young man should have fastened the door upon the inside. There was the possibility that the murderer had done this, and had afterwards escaped by the window. The drop was at least twenty feet, however, and a bed of crocuses in full bloom lay beneath. Neither the flowers nor the earth showed any sign of having been disturbed, nor were there any marks upon the narrow strip of grass which separated the house from the road. Apparently, therefore, it was the young man himself who had fastened the door. But how did he come by his death? No one could have climbed up to the window without leaving traces. Suppose a man had fired through the window, he would indeed be a remarkable shot who could with a revolver inflict so deadly a wound. Again, Park Lane is a frequented thoroughfare; there is a cab stand within a hundred yards of the house. No one had heard a shot.</para>

<para>Если вертикальное пространство меньше, чем 6 строк текста, оставшихся на странице в начале мульти-колонок, разрыв страницы будет вставлен перед этими колонками. В зависимости от количества строк текста введения вы можете изменить размер этого пространства. Это делается путем установки курсора во вставку из нескольких колонок за введением (если таковое имеется) и используя меню <emphasis role='sans'>Вставка&#x21D2;Пробел перед разрывом страницы</emphasis>. Вставьте во вставку требуемую величину промежутка, например, «5cm».</para>
<para>В следующем примере вертикальное расстояние установлено на 7 текстовых строк с помощью <code>7\baselineskip</code> (где команда <code>\baselineskip</code> должна быть вставлена как TeX-код):</para>
<para>On the evening of the crime, he returned from the club exactly at ten. His mother and sister were out spending the evening with a relation. The servant deposed that she heard him enter the front room on the second floor, generally used as his sitting-room. She had lit a fire there, and as it smoked she had opened the window. No sound was heard from the room until eleven-twenty, the hour of the return of Lady Maynooth and her daughter. Desiring to say good-night, she attempted to enter her son's room. The door was locked on the inside, and no answer could be got to their cries and knocking. Help was obtained, and the door forced. The unfortunate young man was found lying near the table. His head had been horribly mutilated by an expanding revolver bullet, but no weapon of any sort was to be found in the room.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Окружающее пространство</title>
<para>Размер пространства до и после нескольких колонок можно изменить с помощью <code>\multicolsep</code>. Например, команда</para>
<programlisting language='lyx'>\setlength{\multicolsep}{3cm}</programlisting>
<para>в TeX-коде меняет значение на 3&#x2009;см. Изменение необходимо сделать до начала колонок. Предустановленное значение — 13&#x2009;pt.</para>
<para>Для этого примера <code>\multicolsep</code> устанавливается в 2.5&#x2009;cm:</para>
<!-- \setlength{\multicolsep}{2.5cm} --><para>All day I turned these facts over in my mind, endeavouring to hit upon some theory which could reconcile them all, and to find that line of least resistance which my poor friend had declared to be the starting-point of every investigation. I confess that I made little progress. In the evening I strolled across the Park, and found myself about six o'clock at the Oxford Street end of Park Lane. A group of loafers upon the pavements, all staring up at a particular window, directed me to the house which I had come to see. A tall, thin man with coloured glasses, whom I strongly suspected of being a plain-clothes detective, was pointing out some theory of his own, while the others crowded round to listen to what he said. I got as near him as I could, but his observations seemed to me to be absurd, so I withdrew again in some disgust. As I did so I struck against an elderly, deformed man, who had been behind me, and I knocked down several books which he was carrying.</para>
<!-- \setlength{\multicolsep}{13pt} --></section>
<section>
<title>Разрывы колонок</title>
<para>Разрыв колонки можно принудительно выполнить, вставив команду <code>\columnbreak{}</code> в TeX-коде в ту позицию в тексте, где колонка должна быть разорвана. Обратите внимание, что в большинстве случаев это приводит к появлению пробелов в тексте.</para>
<para>Пример:</para>
<para>&#8220;You're surprised to see me, sir,&#8221; said he, in a strange, croaking voice.I acknowledged that I was.&#8220;Well, I've a conscience, sir, and when I chanced to see you go into this house, as I came hobbling after you, I thought to myself, I'll just step in and see that kind gentleman, and tell him that if I was a bit gruff in my manner there was not any harm meant, and that I am much obliged to him for picking up my books.&#8221;&#8220;You make too much of a trifle,&#8221; said I. &#8220;May I ask how you knew who I was?&#8221; AFTER THIS SENTENCE THE COLUMN BREAK IS FORCED.<!-- \columnbreak{} -->&#8220;Well, sir, if it isn't too great a liberty, I am a neighbour of yours, for you'll find my little bookshop at the corner of Church Street, and very happy to see you, I am sure. Maybe you collect yourself, sir. Here's British&#xA0;Birds, and Catullus, and The Holy War&#xA0;– a bargain, every one of them. With five volumes you could just fill that gap on that second shelf. It looks untidy, does it not, sir?&#8221;</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Разделение колонок</title>
<para>Ширина колонок рассчитывается автоматически, но вы можете изменить расстояние между ними. Это делается с помощью команды <code>\columnsep</code>. Ее предопределенное значение — 10&#x2009;pt. Пример установки значения для <code>\columnsep</code>:</para>
<!-- \setlength{\columnsep}{3cm} --><para>My observations of No. 427 Park Lane did little to clear up the problem in which I was interested. The house was separated from the street by a low wall and railing, the whole not more than five feet high. It was perfectly easy, therefore, for anyone to get into the garden, but the window was entirely inaccessible, since there was no water pipe or anything which could help the most active man to climb it. More puzzled than ever, I retraced my steps to Kensington. I had not been in my study five minutes when the maid entered to say that a person desired to see me. To my astonishment it was none other than my strange old book collector, his sharp, wizened face peering out from a frame of white hair, and his precious volumes, a dozen of them at least, wedged under his right arm.</para>
<!-- \setlength{\columnsep}{10pt} --></section>
<section>
<title>Вертикальные линии</title>
<para>Между столбцами помещается линия толщиной, задаваемой <code>\columnseprule</code>. Если толщина устанавливается в 0&#x2009;pt (это значение по умолчанию), линия не проводится. В следующем примере ширина разделительной линии составляет 2&#x2009;pt:</para>
<!-- \setlength{\columnseprule}{2pt} --><para>&#8220;You're surprised to see me, sir,&#8221; said he, in a strange, croaking voice.I acknowledged that I was.&#8220;Well, I've a conscience, sir, and when I chanced to see you go into this house, as I came hobbling after you, I thought to myself, I'll just step in and see that kind gentleman, and tell him that if I was a bit gruff in my manner there was not any harm meant, and that I am much obliged to him for picking up my books.&#8221;&#8220;You make too much of a trifle,&#8221; said I. &#8220;May I ask how you knew who I was?&#8221;&#8220;Well, sir, if it isn't too great a liberty, I am a neighbour of yours, for you'll find my little bookshop at the corner of Church Street, and very happy to see you, I am sure. Maybe you collect yourself, sir. Here's British&#xA0;Birds, and Catullus, and The Holy War&#xA0;– a bargain, every one of them. With five volumes you could just fill that gap on that second shelf. It looks untidy, does it not, sir?&#8221;</para>

<para>Линию можно вывести в цвете, переопределив <code>\columnseprulecolor</code>. Это делается путем вставки команды</para>
<programlisting language='lyx'>\renewcommand{\columnseprulecolor}{\color{red}}</programlisting>
<para>как TeX-кода перед вставкой мульти-колонок, для получения дополнительной информации о предварительно определенных и само-определенных цветах см. руководство <emphasis>Встроенные объекты, раздел <emphasis>Цветные таблицы. Чтобы вернуться к цвету по умолчанию, вставьте команду</emphasis></emphasis></para>
<programlisting language='lyx'>\renewcommand{\columnseprulecolor}{\normalcolor}</programlisting>
<para>Пример с линией голубого цвета и расстоянием между колонками в 1&#x2009;см:</para>
<!-- \setlength{\columnsep}{1cm}
\renewcommand{\columnseprulecolor}{\color{cyan}} --><para>&#8220;You're surprised to see me, sir,&#8221; said he, in a strange, croaking voice.I acknowledged that I was.&#8220;Well, I've a conscience, sir, and when I chanced to see you go into this house, as I came hobbling after you, I thought to myself, I'll just step in and see that kind gentleman, and tell him that if I was a bit gruff in my manner there was not any harm meant, and that I am much obliged to him for picking up my books.&#8221;&#8220;You make too much of a trifle,&#8221; said I. &#8220;May I ask how you knew who I was?&#8221;&#8220;Well, sir, if it isn't too great a liberty, I am a neighbour of yours, for you'll find my little bookshop at the corner of Church Street, and very happy to see you, I am sure. Maybe you collect yourself, sir. Here's British&#xA0;Birds, and Catullus, and The Holy War&#xA0;– a bargain, every one of them. With five volumes you could just fill that gap on that second shelf. It looks untidy, does it not, sir?&#8221;</para>
<!-- \setlength{\columnseprule}{0pt}
\renewcommand{\columnseprulecolor}{\normalcolor} --></section>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>